Chris: Software should only be released
after it has gone through a proper process
of development, testing and bug fixing.
Testing is a critical component of the
development process looking at areas such
as ‘performance’, ‘stability’ and ‘error
handling’ by setting up test scenarios under
controlled conditions and assessing the results.
Leah: There are generally four recognized
levels of testing, ‘unit or component
testing’, ‘integration testing’, ‘system
testing’, and ‘acceptance testing’.
Let’s look at these more closely.
Chris: Unit Testing is the first level, where
specific lines of code, distinct functionalities,
and desired procedures are isolated and tested.
These are termed ‘software units’ because they
are combined to make up the software but are
also referred to as ‘components’ of the software.
Leah: For example, a line of code in a
“calculator software” can have the function of
implementing ‘+’ “addition,” while another line
of code implements ‘x’ “multiplication,” etc.
These and other functions of the calculator
software must be individually tested, to
ensure that the calculator operates flawlessly.
Chris: Integration Testing involves combining
all the components that make up the software,
and testing ‘everything as a whole’,
instead of individually, as in unit testing.
From this level, tests can be split into
‘functional’ and ‘non-functional’ types which
we will look at further later in this session.
So why is integration testing important?
Leah: A large team of developers working on
a project will be responsible for writing
different parts of the code, which will
require testing to ensure that it is correct.
By testing, we can identify and correct
faults such as ‘inter-working defects’,
‘simultaneous operation defects’, ‘parallel
operation defects’ amongst others.
‘Integration testing’ ascertains how well the
units of code work together, and the condition
of the interfaces between each of them.
Sometimes, a line of code may work properly
when tested alone, however, when combined with
other lines of code to achieve the desired
function, an error may occur, indicating
that the integration of one or more lines
of code into the rest was unsuccessful.
Chris: System testing is carried out to
verify that software operates as required
and is compatible with operating systems.
It tests both the technical and business
logic of the software using ‘functional tests’
on the various ‘functions’ of a system, and
‘non-functional tests’ on how those work.
There have been cases where the Android
version of an application may function
correctly, but the iOS version has issues.
All the software’s completed versions are
tested on all the possible operating systems,
to ensure all platform functionality.
A functional test may check if a login feature
responds when the user enters a password,
and a non-functional test may check how long
it takes to log in after password entry.
Leah: System testing can expose such
errors and allow developers to detect
and correct them before launch.
It also looks at how good the
design of the software is.
The internal code may work fine, but the outward
design might have some operational issues.
The overall behaviour of the software is another
aspect that system testing helps to authenticate.
It may be well developed but still malfunctions,
due to the different system specifications.
System testing helps identify any abnormal
behaviour and helps organisations to outline
the software’s best system specifications.
Chris: Acceptance Testing also referred
to as User Acceptance Testing is similar
to the system testing, but the test is
carried out by some selected end-users.
This stage determines if the software is finally
ready to be launched to the general public.
The selected users give their various opinions
about the operation of the software letting
the organization know if it meets their diverse
requirements or how it can be improved upon.
Organisations may conduct acceptance testing
using their own specifics, but ideally
users will be selected from a range of
demographics, different operating systems, and
past experiences of using similar software.
There are two types of ‘Acceptance Testing’
these are ‘Alpha and Beta Testing’.
Leah: Alpha testing is carried out by selected
users, alongside an internal team of developers
who control the testing environment aiming
to mimic realistic conditions during testing.
The selected users are given access to the
developer’s platform and allowed to use and
test the developed software or application.
During ‘alpha testing’, minor
errors can still be found and fixed.
Chris: Beta testing is carried out by selected
users on their own devices and operating systems.
Here, the finished software is sent to
the selected users, to use and test it
over time and then provide feedback.
At the ‘beta level’, the software is expected
to run perfectly, and meet the end user’s needs.